<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/refs/heads/main/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <title># 🇱🇰 Sri Lanka This Week</title>
    <link>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/README.md</link>
    <description>*Generated by [gpt-5](https://platform.openai.com/docs/models/gpt-5) from **181** English News Articles published between **2025-11-06** &amp; **2025-11-13**.*</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Budget 2026 swaps crisis-fighting for reform rhetoric but leaves growth to execution</title>
      <description>President Anura Kumara Dissanayake’s second Budget locks in IMF-style consolidation while signalling a pivot to investment-led growth. It trims recurrent excess, proposes PPP and investment-protection laws, opens state land for vetted FDI, and dangles residence visas for investors. Markets cheered: the CSE hit fresh highs and Fitch praised the fiscal path. Business, from the Ceylon Chamber to apparel brands, welcomed policy stability but asked for faster, clearer implementation, especially on trade facilitation, SOE/PPP laws and investor incentives. The sting is the VAT net widening (threshold down to Rs. 36m) and a still-modest capital push. A plantation wage hike to Rs. 1,750 is popular but needs productivity and value-add to avoid margin squeeze. As ever, the test is delivery, not design. 📈</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#1-budget-2026-swaps-crisisfighting-for-reform-rhetoric-but-leaves-growth-to-execution</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Governance moves from slogan to systems as regulators warn boards and courts probe ministers</title>
      <description>The SEC used a well-attended Colombo teach-in to remind directors that liabilities are real—under the Companies Act boards face dozens of civil and over a hundred criminal exposures. Beneficial-ownership rules and solvency tests are moving from compliance to culture. That sits uneasily with political theatre: former Tourism Minister Prasanna Ranatunga was arrested by the Bribery Commission and bailed—an emblem of due process, not yet of deterrence. If anti-corruption is to be more than headlines, procurement, independence and enforcement must mature together. ⚖️</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#2-governance-moves-from-slogan-to-systems-as-regulators-warn-boards-and-courts-probe-ministers</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democracy and devolution return to the front burner as PCs languish and reparations stall</title>
      <description>The long-frozen Provincial Council (PC) polls resurfaced after former Election Commissioner Mahinda Deshapriya flagged a Supreme Court dictum that Governors cannot run provinces indefinitely. The Socialist Alliance demanded dates or a legal workaround to run under PR until delimitation ends. Meanwhile ITAK warned the President that appointing more ex-security officials to the Office of Reparations would gut credibility—three of five members would be from security services if two nominees go through. For a government courting investors and EU trade preferences, strengthening rule of law and reconciliation is not just ethics—it is economics. 🧭</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#3-democracy-and-devolution-return-to-the-front-burner-as-pcs-languish-and-reparations-stall</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sex education becomes a culture war even as data demand action on child wellbeing</title>
      <description>Cardinal Malcolm Ranjith denounced a planned sexual-education module as foreign-imposed and morally corrosive. The Prime Minister, who also holds Education, defended age-appropriate lessons backed by the Health Ministry, Family Health Bureau and the National Child Protection Authority, citing rising abuse cases and safety needs. In parallel, academics questioned rushed psychometric testing in schools and warned of the pitfalls of high-stakes literacy/numeracy regimes. With studies pointing to widespread childhood depression, reforms need transparent curricula, trained teachers and parental trust—less polemic, more evidence. 🧠</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#4-sex-education-becomes-a-culture-war-even-as-data-demand-action-on-child-wellbeing</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital drive accelerates from awards to architecture—but trust and privacy must keep pace</title>
      <description>Sri Lanka’s tech agenda is busy: INFOTEL pushed the $15b digital-economy target; OnsysConnect won a national award for secure data exchange across agencies; a MOSIP-based Unique Digital ID moved to the vendor shortlist (Infosys, TCS and others), with a local operator handover built in; and a PR blueprint urged pairing infrastructure with stakeholder trust. The PPP Act and an Investment Protection Act are slated for early 2026. Success will hinge on clean data governance, cybersecurity, and clear user consent. 🧑‍💻</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#5-digital-drive-accelerates-from-awards-to-architecturebut-trust-and-privacy-must-keep-pace</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trade and ties broaden as Colombo courts capital and neighbours</title>
      <description>Sri Lanka pitched at the Shanghai CIIE with tea, gems and coconut wares; welcomed Asia-Pacific business leaders to Colombo for CACCI; and set up a Sri Lanka–Saudi business council alongside ministerial talks. At home, Port City incentives are being fine-tuned and residence visas for investors offered. The PPP framework is due in Q1. Yet exporters and SMEs still face tight credit, skills gaps and trade-policy drift. Concluding deeper, rules-based FTAs and fixing customs-to-port frictions would turn receptions into receipts.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#6-trade-and-ties-broaden-as-colombo-courts-capital-and-neighbours</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corporate results and the bourse’s bull run buy time for reforms</title>
      <description>Banks, insurers and conglomerates—Sunshine, Ambeon, HNB Assurance, Mahindra Ideal Finance—reported solid quarters as the CSE’s ASPI cleared 23,000. Sector lobbies—from apparel (SLABA) to women’s enterprise (WCIC)—praised the Budget’s direction but cautioned on VAT burdens for SMEs and the need for export competitiveness. Tourism’s labour crunch returned, with calls to retain and upskill staff; the government proposed a plantation wage rise and lauded a century of the Tea Research Institute. Earnings strength gives breathing space; competitiveness will keep it. 💼</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#7-corporate-results-and-the-bourses-bull-run-buy-time-for-reforms</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crime and security policy narrow the space for narco-networks but widen the need for social care</title>
      <description>Seven Sri Lankan drug traffickers hiding in the Middle East reportedly offered to surrender amid a nationwide anti-drug drive, underscoring cross-border coordination gains. Regional volatility—from Islamabad’s suicide bombing to a blast near Delhi’s Red Fort—keeps Sri Lanka’s security services on alert. At home, hard enforcement must be matched with prevention: schools, communities and rehabilitation. Without that, crackdowns risk displacement rather than dismantling. 🚔</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:06:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://github.com/nuuuwan/lk_news_digest/blob/main/data/readme_history/README.20251113.120633.md#8-crime-and-security-policy-narrow-the-space-for-narconetworks-but-widen-the-need-for-social-care</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
